[Music]
So, whenever I'm out detecting at the
park or pretty much anywhere there's a
crowd of people, it seems like I always
get approached by someone who's
interested in the hobby. And generally,
their first question to me is, "What's a
good detector to get started with?" Now,
they're obviously not going to be buying
any of these high-end units. So, I
usually tell them to check out something
in the $250 to $300 price range.
something like a M Lab Extera Pro or a
Nocta simplex or something along those
lines. But, you know, $250 to $300 can
still be a lot of money for somebody
who's not even sure if they're going to
stick with the hobby. So, that got me
thinking, what are some good options
that are less than
$200? Well, over the next few months,
I'm going to take a look at a few of
them. I want to check out the Mine Lab
Vanquish 340 series, uh the Knock the
Findex series, and maybe a few others,
but I'm not going to be looking at the
really cheap ones on Amazon, like the uh
$50 to $75 deals, because I've bought
those for my grandkids in the past, and
they were basically garbage, not even
usable. So, anyway, today we're going to
look at a new one from Dr. OTCH called
the MT12. They reached out a few weeks
ago and asked if I'd be interested in
doing a review. And having used some of
their other detectors in the past, I
know they're pretty decent. So, I
replied back and said, "You know, I
don't do promotional videos, but if
you're okay with an honest review where
I point out the good and the bad, then
yeah, send it on." Well, they did, and
here we are. Now, they did send the
detector for free for the purpose of the
review, but that's not going to affect
my opinion whatsoever. Matter of fact,
I've already got way too many detectors,
so I'll probably just end up doing a
giveaway on this one in the future. They
were also nice enough to send out their
MT6 Pro pinpointer. And I've actually
done a review on this one in the past,
and I'll put a link down below if you
want to check it out. But long story
short, for the money, it's a really good
pinpointer. All right, so I'll give you
a quick look at the box, then we'll do
an unboxing, go over the controls, maybe
do some air test, then we'll go try it
out in the field. All right, let me
switch cameras and we'll get started.
[Music]
Heat up
here.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Okay, so we got it put together. Getting
those batteries in there was kind of a
pain in the ass, but everything else was
pretty
easy.
Overall, I'd say it feels pretty good.
It's not heavy at all. It's not super
light. doesn't feel
cheap. Feels like a good improvement
over the previous
models. Right off the bat, a couple of
things I like is number one, they went
with a keyed shaft. And what I mean by
that is it's not round. For whatever
reason, even on some of these more
expensive detectors like this
manor, they use a round shaft and every
time you use it, you have to line up the
coil, which I'm not a big fan of.
Another improvement I see is they've
switched from those pin locks to the cam
locks here. And these actually feel
really
good. And for whatever reason, they have
the uh little short stem here that
connects to the coil separated from the
other part of the lower
shaft. I'm not sure why they did that.
Maybe to reduce
flex. I don't know. But it's going to
limit you as far as how far you can
collapse it down. Not a huge
deal. It still collapses down pretty
small. I believe you can collapse down
this section, too. Let's see.
Yeah. So, yeah, it collapses down to a
fairly small
package. Now, they've included some
headphones that feel pretty decent.
They're wired headphones.
Looks like it has a volume control in
line. And they give you the carrying
bag, which I've never actually used, but
I'm sure it's decent
quality. And one of the things I like
that they include with their detectors
is these Dr. Rotek hand diggers. I've
used these in the past, and they're
actually really
good. Saves you a little bit of money
right there.
It's about the same size
as my other digger, which is from
Predator
Tools. Like I said, I've used these in
the past and they hold up pretty well.
So, that's a nice little extra. A lot
better than some of the other cheaper
detectors that only give you those
flimsy collapsible
shovels. All right, so let me read
through the manual, then we'll go over
the controls.
Okay, we'll take just a minute to go
over the controls. This knob on the left
is going to power the machine on and off
as well as adjust the
sensitivity. Now, when you first turn it
on, it's going to go through its system
check, but it'll beep to let you know
when it's
done. There we go. Turning it clockwise,
you can see it's increasing the
sensitivity, counterclockwise to
decrease. All right. On the opposite
side is how we switch from
discrimination mode to all metal mode as
well as control the threshold
volume. Switching to all metal. As we
turn it clockwise, you'll start to hear
the
threshold. Okay. Also, while in all
metal mode, if you press and hold the
menu/ground grab key and pump the coil,
it'll give you a ground balance as well
as your ground balance numbers on the
bottom right. Okay. This is obviously
your battery meter. This is your ID
scale across the top as well as some
icons here at the bottom is how you go
into pinpoint mode. Press and release
once to go to pinpoint mode. Press and
release again to go back to your regular
detect
mode. Okay. When you click menu, it's
going to bring up the backlight, which
has nine different
levels. And you're obviously not going
to be able to see it out here because
it's too bright, but you can take my
word for it. Press it again. Goes to
volume. It also has nine
levels. Okay. Press it again and it
brings up notch width. And this is how
you control how many numbers you want to
notch out or notch in at one
time. Okay. Press it again. Goes to
notch. And this is where you actually go
through and notch out whatever you want
or don't want to
detect.
Okay, one more goes to beach mode. And
I'm nowhere near beach, so we won't be
testing that one out. All right, the
only thing I think I forgot to mention
is that the headphone jack is on the
back side
there. All right, guys. So, we all know
the air tests are not going to be the
same as targets buried in the ground,
but I think it'll at least give us a
general idea of what kind of depth we
can expect, best case scenario, and what
the target ID will be on some common
targets. So, today I brought out a few
coins and a few rings. I have a uh
Indian head penny, a B- nickel, a Barber
dime, a Barber quarter, a Barber half, a
Morgan dollar, a small silver ring, 10
karat wedding band, and a 14 karat ring.
So, I've got the sensitivity about as
high as I can go without getting too
much EMI. It's about 3/4 of the way. I'm
going to back it off just a little bit
because I hear it
chirping. Anyway, we'll take a look at
these targets and see what we get.
Okay, so this is a three-tone machine.
So on iron, you're going to get a low
grunt. On uh midc conductors, you're
going to get a midtone. For nickels,
probably all the way up to Indian head
pennies. And on high conductors like
dimes, quarters, halves, and dollars,
you'll get a high
tone. All right. So we'll start out with
the Indian head penny.
Looks like it cuts out around 6 and 12
inches. Next up is a B-
nickel right around 7
in. Next up is a Barber
dime. So it starts to cut out around 6
in. Next up is a barber
quarter. Cuts out around 6 and 1/2
in. Here we have a barber
[Music]
half starts to cut out around 7
in. Morgan
dollar cuts out around 7 and 1/2 or 8
in. Here we have a small silver
ring. Cuts out around 6
in. Here we have a 10 karat gold wedding
band. So, we hit that out almost to 8
in. Seems to like gold better than
silver. Here we have a 14 karat gold
ring.
7 and 12 or 8 in. Now, keep in mind I'm
in the city, so I have to keep the
sensitivity reasonable. You might get a
little better depth out in the
country. I've been here at the park for
about an hour now with the MT12. Just
trying to get used to the machine, and
so far it's done pretty good. I've
already found several coins, but the uh
the pinpoint feature seems a little bit
wonky to me. Now, that could be just
because I'm not used to it yet. But
anyway, I've already marked off a few
targets here that we can take a look at
together. I guess a ball game just ended
or something because there's a lot of
people headed out, but we'll wait on
some of this traffic to clear out before
we
continue. Nothing really runs all that
deep here, but there is a lot of trash.
So, I've got the discrimination set up
for coin shooting. Anyway, here we are
at the first target.
Hopefully you can see that
screen. That's reading 76 to
78. I'm going to guess that's the uh
copper penny range.
[Music]
Maybe a little too deep to hit with a
pinpointer. This ground's really tough.
[Music]
We'll let that motorcycle
pass. All right. So, it seems to be
right there.
There we go. It is a
coin. It's going to be a copper
penny
memorial. All right. Next target.
Okay, target number
two. This one's reading solid 85
86. I'm going to guess that's the
quarter range.
[Music]
Okay, that one's in the plug.
There it
is. And it is going to be a
quarter. All right. Two for two on the
coins. Okay. Target number
three. This one's reading 79 to 81. That
might be in the dime
range. Or it could be a copper penny.
[Music]
Little bit deeper.
I saw it right there. It
is. That's going to be a clad
dime. Three for three on the coins.
Okay, target number
four. 86 87. That's another one in the
quarter range.
This ground is
tough. Yep, there it
is. Another
quarter. Four for four on coins. That's
not too
shabby. All right, so this is obviously
not going to be a full review, but just
my initial impressions after a couple
hours of use. Uh, we'll start out with a
good. I like the new keyed shaft and cam
locks. I like the overall feel and
weight of the detector. Like the large
display, the control knobs. I like that
it remembers the settings that you last
used. The target ID is large and easy to
read. And the target ID is also
stable. I like the ability to notch out
individual numbers or ranges. I like the
included hand digger. And one thing I
like about this company, Dr. Protek is
they're not afraid of a little
constructive criticism, which I'm about
to give right now. Okay, let's talk
about a few things that I didn't care
for or things I'd like to see them fix
on future models. Number one would be
the pinpoint mode. Now, while it did
work, it just seemed a little bit
strange to me. I noticed sometimes when
I pinpoint a target and then lift the
coil off the ground, the uh pinpoint
audio would continue to sound off. I'll
put up a short video so that you can see
what I mean.
Number two is the 9volt batteries. And
this goes for all manufacturers that are
still using 9volt and double A
batteries. It's 2025. I see no reason
why these detectors shouldn't have
rechargeable lithium batteries. Okay.
Number two, I'd like to see more tone
options. Now, the tones on this detector
are good, but they're a little bit short
or clipped. While that's probably good
for separation, it's not so great for
trying to gauge the size of a target.
So, more audio options. And finally,
using the notch settings needs to be
explained a little more clearly, keeping
in mind the target audience for this
detector is probably going to include a
lot of beginners, and even I had trouble
getting it set up right at
first. All right, let's talk pricing.
Now, this detector is going to retail
for $199, but anybody who knows Dr. OTH
knows that they almost always have
coupons for 30 or $40 off. Matter of
fact, I just checked their Amazon
listing, and at the time of this video,
they have a $30 off coupon plus another
15% off, which I believe brings the
total price to somewhere around
$149. And when you take into
consideration they're giving you a nice
free handheld digger that's probably
worth at least 25 bucks. That's not a
bad deal. All right, I'll include links
to the detector and the pinpointer down
in the description if you want to check
it out. And there you have it. That's my
review of the Dr. OTCH MT12.
[Music]